I am...
I have lost all my illusions.
I expect anything.
Nothing reassures me anymore.
And especially now.
Especially now.
I'm so scared because everything is so uncertain that I keep thinking that from one day to the next,
Something can happen before we even have time to realize it.
THE
Forgiveness makes no sense to me.
There are some things that are absolutely unforgivable.
I don't see why I should forgive them.
and in particular,
No one has ever asked me for forgiveness.
Nothing can surprise us because we have an extremely pessimistic philosophy of humanity.
I believe that men are capable of both the worst and the best.
that there are two categories of men.
Those who are incapable
to be ferocious beasts and then those who remained primitive.
And
The nightmare began like this.
I remember we had a bench,
We were sitting,
both,
Because my father meant everything to me.
We were leaning back to back and we were both devouring each other.
And then there was a kind of furious madness,
Everything was abandoned, and so people would steal from the train carriages at the station.
they left with tons of cans of peas,
of sardines,
pasta,
In short, it was really a kind of madness.
We knew the danger was there.
But what could we do?
We didn't have...
Where to go?
No one came to tell us,
I can hide from you,
Perhaps we could have done as some others have done,
to try to cross the demarcation line,
But with what means?
To go where?
To go somewhere else?
Good,
We stayed.
And everything was forbidden.
We shouldn't have left the city.
We shouldn't have gathered together.
You shouldn't go out in the street at just any time of day.
And outside, one could hear cries from the bone,
the bone,
schnell,
heraus and machine gun fire.
But all of that,
It's happening.
It seems so unreal,
We don't know if we're dreaming.
if that's the reality.
I was completely paralyzed,
There were only corpses.
There was just one baby,
I knew that baby well,
He was 18 months old.
who was screaming amidst his corpses.
There was a lot of blood.
I couldn't move my body.
And this baby,
It haunts me to this day because I feel a little guilty for not having had the strength to go and get that child.
Resistance had grown throughout this period, and German officers were beginning to be killed here and there.
in Paris,
in Nantes,
in Bordeaux.
I mainly did transport of equipment.
of all kinds,
newspapers and sometimes weapons,
Sticks of dynamite or things like that,
panniers from my bike to take them here and there.
I was mainly part of the armed group.
The application of Pétain's anti-Semitic legislation,
which he put in place as early as October 1940,
will be implemented gradually.
It didn't...
I played so much on my father's arrest on December 12, 1941,
because he was arrested by the Germans,
by the Gestapo
as a hostage among a thousand prominent Jews.
And me and my mother,
We will be taken on July 16th.
1942 as part of the arafle which you know as the Veldif arafle.
We were evicted from our home along with the others.
all the Jews were herded into a neighborhood.
There was ghetto A and ghetto B.
Ghetto A consisted of young people who were fit for work and useful to the
3rd rail,
to production.
And ghetto B was packed with people who didn't have time.
deport them,
nor assassinate them.
So, families who were bringing things back from elsewhere.
And those people,
They didn't care about them at all.
There were no supplies,
There was nothing there.
When the doorbell rang at our door
July 16th, morning,
I could have chosen not to open it.
But my mother told me "open it".
We had prepared some things,
We didn't know what was going to happen.
And in front of our door,
There were French police officers.
And I would also like to remind everyone that on that day, only foreign or stateless Jews were rounded up.
it was kind of the...
The screen or the protection of the French Israelites.
And what I saw was something atrocious.
There were corpses in the streets,
They were just kids holding hands,
with the snotty-nosed child in tears,
who wandered the streets,
They probably had no one left.
that they no longer had parents.
In this closed ghetto,
It was just me and my two brothers,
No one from the family left.
Everyone was deported.
assassinated.
When the door opened,
I saw
Goldilocks,
I knew it was over.
So he recognized me immediately, of course.
but he didn't report me within a minute.
It has settled down,
It looked like a wounded animal.
Then he looked at each girl individually and said no.
No.
I was saying, as long as they don't recognize me.
I prayed to God that they wouldn't recognize me.
And then finally he made up his mind and then he chose me.
He said it was her.
Then the German said,
the German, sorry.
the guy with the mouth.
The Gestapo said
"It's Annick."
The head of the office said "no,
No,
her name is not
"Annick." She declined to give my name.
And then they took me to the
The Gestapo, which was three steps further on,
on the same street opposite.
Two others recognized me again.
There were 24 of us arrested.
Those two who recognized me didn't talk much.
They did not overwhelm us.
THANKS.
But really, the Germans were fully aware of our entire organization.
of our activities,
They were fully aware of everything.
We were ordered to assemble in a large square,
This was the old bus station.
and we were forced to kneel with our hands behind our necks.
And they proceeded with the selection.
That's how, in the liquidation of the ghetto,
My brother
Kadek has disappeared.
And next to me,
There was a woman I knew.
She had just had a baby.
This baby was 15 days old.
She was next to me,
They ordered him to stand up.
to move forward.
And given that she had the baby,
necessarily,
She was going to the group that we knew wasn't good.
And nothing was happening calmly.
Each person...
He indicated his direction.
a lash of the whip,
a kick,
And that woman,
She tripped.
And the baby fell.
And two soldiers,
They were probably drunk.
It's impossible that it was any other way.
They started playing football with this child.
And this mother,
She turned around and received a blow to the head with a whip.
And she left.
On September 25th,
when we were made to get off our wagons at Bestiaux,
They separated us men.
and women.
Afterwards,
In the middle of the ramp, there were covered trucks that had stopped.
towards which the children were directed,
the old people,
disabled people,
the injured,
elderly people.
I didn't even see my mother get into the truck.
And we left.
afterwards,
We counted ourselves in a convoy of 1000 men.
women,
children,
only 26 women at the Birkenau camp.
We didn't understand anything.
We were starting to wonder why the trucks hadn't arrived before us.
And when we asked the hood why the trucks weren't arriving,
She gestured for us to go towards the windows.
And looking out the windows,
She showed us chimneys that were smoking.
And she immediately explained to us that...
Those who had not followed us on foot into the camp,
They had passed by there.
She told us about the gas chambers and crematoria that were smoking and turning the sky red.
SO,
practically the evening of my arrival,
I knew I would never see my mother again.
I still held onto hope of finding my father.
So we spent our first night in this sauna block because the initiation ceremonies didn't start until the next day.
I forgot to mention that on the day of our arrival,
THE
September 25
1942 my mother,
It was his birthday.
She was just 50 years old.
We were stripped naked,
They shaved our heads and they tattooed us.
And that's what Auschwitz was special about.
The tattoo,
that's to say...
Good,
My mother told me that as soon as we arrived.
when we put down our handbag,
that we no longer had an identity,
That was true.
One fine day,
We met up again,
the 24th,
in trucks,
on buses,
I believe, moreover,
and then on a train that took us to Frennes.
All 24 of us were together.
We were shown into an extremely well-laid-out room,
Black and red flags everywhere
Hitler's portrait at the very back,
the judges in their full judicial robes.
It was extremely impressive.
There were soldiers all along the walls.
They make us stand up,
They make us get up.
And then begins the spiel.
the president of the court.
And gradually,
The interpreter repeated what the president was saying.
The first nine,
And I wasn't one of them.
sentenced to death.
It certainly made quite an impression on me.
But all of a sudden I thought I wasn't going to be.
Besides, I never thought I would be sentenced to death.
I didn't think I was strong enough for that.
The first nine people sentenced to death for aggression against the German army,
equipment deterioration
etc.
Good,
and they continue for the next seven.
They were also sentenced to death.
So, them,
for assistance to the enemies of Germany,
to those who were degrading,
We had assisted them.
I was one of those seven.
The beach of
Goethe, the camp commandant,
He enjoyed shooting people.
He arrived at a gallop,
on a white horse,
with a dog.
of Almatian who followed the horse and then he shot at everything that moved.
And that's how it is.
A day,
There was a woman who fell at my feet and I turned around,
I was watching him.
And I saw that he was thriving.
He was pleased with himself.
And he had...
He had fantasies like that.
He was quite a character...
Throughout my deportation,
from all sides...
the most,
I don't dare say the craziest one because it wouldn't be his fault if I said he was crazy.
but the most bestial,
I don't know what it was made of.
But he loved blood,
Barbarity killed.
It was,
I read afterwards that he was a very ordinary man.
And it's often ordinary men,
who gained a certain amount of power during the war,
who allowed themselves the most horrible things.
I always believed that it wasn't only the Germans who could be capable of things like that.
In France, too, one could be like that.
And you can see the proof.
They tortured people in Algeria.
we have...
My despair over painful events is not limited to what is happening in Europe.
everywhere,
both in South America and in Africa.
anywhere in the world where there are crimes like the one in Rwanda.
Of course it provoked our anger.
our sadness,
Our despair too.
Having lived,
It still seems crazy to me that things like that could happen after the Second World War.
But like everyone else,
no doubt
We get used to the worst.
I don't know how to explain it.
It's painful.
Yes,
That's for sure.
A profound pain, even.
Me,
personally,
I have never denied that there were genocides before the Nazi camps and that there have been genocides since.
I know that not all of my colleagues will agree to even using the expression "concentration camp".
which they readily reserve for extermination in the Nazi camp,
But it exists elsewhere and in other forms.
Of course.
I do not hold young Germans responsible,
even though I know that there are still far-right groups.
There are Nazis in Germany.
But anyway,
There are some in France too.
The Battle of Stalingrad would reverse the course of history.
In a few months,
The flag of the Soviet Union will once again fly over the city.
50,000 Russian soldiers and almost three times as many German soldiers would lose their lives on the battlefield.
Another 120,000 will be taken prisoner.
The defeat of the German 6th Army will shake the Third Reich.
SO,
We would put our ear to the ground to feel if the earth was resonating.
And that's where they gradually began sending people to Auschwitz.
We were all naked.
We were afraid.
because there,
We were overwhelmed by the smell and the smoke.
And it was nervous,
We were banging on it.
They were doing it to us.
since there was no way to go to the toilet.
And then perhaps fear,
It was hellish.
All the smells mingled.
One fine morning,
very early on,
at dawn,
We heard a noise.
We were very scared.
It stopped at our cell.
We said to ourselves,
That's it.
And the guy came and read us something that said the 14 boys were...
They were shot within the hour, and we were...
that we would be sent to Germany,
that the Führer in his great kindness was granting us a respite, we were not pardoned, and that our fate would depend on our attitude in Germany.
So I stayed in Lübeck for three months and then after three months we were
An entire group from Lubeck prison was sent to Côte-Bus.
And on July 14th,
we told our caretakers,
Today is the national holiday and we are on strike.
We are not working.
And that's what we did.
Then we danced,
sung,
The Marseillaise was born in Nipotin.
And there you have it.
The Gestapo came.
They regretted it a great deal,
the guards,
because afterwards the Gestapo was there every day.
And that's where our fate took a turn.
that shortly afterwards we were sent to Ravendzourek.
We were lined up between the electrified barbed wire and the barracks.
We were told to undress and between two rows of
SS, we were made to run for our lives.
SO...
This race can be summarized as follows:
because we knew approximately that at the start there were 6000 of us and at the finish there were 1500 of us.
And the missing ones...
We had been pushed out of the line of this race with rifle butts by the SS on both sides.
We met up again,
I don't know exactly which space,
and we were harangued by the camp commander who told us that we had been chosen to live.
while we saw the trucks on which thousands of our comrades were being loaded, who were going to die that day,
and that they were taken to the gas chambers,
that we could hear screaming,
so that I don't remember anything else from the speech.
from the camp commandant because we could hear our comrades screaming their heads off because there,
They knew where they were going.
We can't say what we...
What exactly one feels when standing in this complex in front of the crematorium,
with that smell,
this smoke,
and that you are waiting for
How long will this last?
We don't know.
Am I going to collapse?
I don't know.
It's impossible to describe what you feel in that moment.
It's something unreal.
It was a smell of...
Of death,
Please,
of misery,
of...
I don't know,
It was a smell...
Me,
I was enveloped by the smell for a long time.
a long time.
I remember,
a woman who was murmuring a prayer.
I was angry after that.
And then,
there had been a spring,
You see,
I suddenly regained my strength.
my anger.
I was thinking,
But how can she pray?
But how can she think that there is a God?
I was outraged.
And I am a rebel against religion.
even now,
whereas I would like to respect.
Some religions,
There are some very good people,
We need to believe in something.
hang.
I put myself in the place of those people,
It helps them to live.
But when I think that our executioners were believers,
that they greeted each other,
"God with us",
God with us.
Without being able to project themselves into the future,
without believing there would be a future,
We couldn't survive.
But I knew there were political organizations in the camp, so I asked to join the clandestine organization.
let's say from a French-speaking communist party,
because there were French women,
There were Belgians,
At that time there were Dutch women who made up the group.
of French language.
We arrived in a block,
block 32,
which had already been working for a long time.
So there was already a sense of solidarity in place.
So, solidarity,
It was indeed the communists who had initially organized it.
A lot of pregnant women arrived.
So, initially,
They were killed.
she and the baby.
And then,
We only killed babies.
I don't know why,
instead of killing them upon arrival,
We were waiting until they had had the baby.
They killed them both.
Then afterwards,
We only killed the baby.
We let them live.
The children were dying like flies.
We gave milk to the dogs,
but not to children.
SO,
A pair of rubber gloves was stolen from the German doctors.
And we made pacifiers out of the gloves.
It was...
Very complex and very diverse,
solidarity.
Nevertheless, not many children were saved.
even risking his life to help them.
Go steal the dog's milk,
It was incredibly dangerous.
Living conditions were such that survival time was all the more limited because...
The food was insufficient.
The lice were there.
The work was there.
The dogs were there.
The guards and overseers who monitored the internal life of the camp and who accompanied the commandos on their way to work,
Everything was done to make us die.
We were able to...
Resist until you catch typhus.
Good,
I had already seen lice under a microscope in parasitology.
But then we discovered that we have no time.
We were covered in lice.
And it's the louse that transmits the...
Exanthematic typhus.
The trucks have arrived.
And then tragedy struck.
We put the children in the truck,
They were torn away from their mothers who were holding them like that,
And we watched helplessly as it happened.
It was horrific.
Afterwards we were so ashamed of having let it happen.
But anyway,
It was absolutely...
That's my worst memory.
Yes,
this time,
they have...
Then the children were put into the trucks.
The trucks left and, strangely enough,
The mothers were screaming, but the children weren't.
The little twig who was playing with the mess...
The camp leader was clinging to his mother's neck; he didn't shed a tear.
Nothing at all, the camp leader who had just been playing with him snatched her from her mother by the hair, gave the woman a hard blow with a goumi stick, and she collapsed to the ground, unconscious.
I kept thinking, 'Please let her be dead, it's going to be terrible, waking up without her little one, it was awful, really.'
That was the hardest part for me.
That.
I feel no guilt.
But here,
I'm a little ashamed.
I think we should have,
even at the risk of being massacred,
to revolt,
to do something.
We did nothing.
Yes,
We should have.
In fact, we were in tears.
it must be said,
We were in tears.
The Allied armies land in Normandy.
The blood and tears of thousands of men,
civilians and military personnel,
intertwine in one of the greatest battles in history.
In a few months,
France will be liberated.
For some,
This is the end of the war.
For others,
at the gates of hell,
Peace and freedom are still only a hope.
And we were evacuated from Auschwitz,
all camps,
of the entire complex.
Initially,
That made us happy.
We knew we weren't going to be gassed,
because that had been our fear.
Only,
We were being shot at.
When we could no longer move forward,
We saw our comrades falling.
That's why we called all these marches towards other camps,
the death marches.
That's how I got started.
At the end of January,
early February,
at the Ravensbrück camp,
under a tent.
We were wading through water up to our mid-thighs,
That's why we were so cold.
We no longer had a straw mattress,
only a few planks.
Four of us slept on the planks.
So survival and hope were not yet forthcoming.
After that,
by train
via Magdeburg,
We were taken to Leipzig.
We were put back in the train car and we were rolling along like that.
And that's what I forgot to mention previously,
There was a girl who asked...
To the supervisor,
" Madam,
How long are we going to travel like this?
There are dead bodies among us,
There are people who are dying,
We can't take it anymore.
And the answer was,
" Well,
until you all die.
Well then,
We no longer had any illusions.
When we arrived at Mauthausen,
We were made to undress from the beginning of the night to take our clothes away, supposedly for disinfection.
So we were very cold.
All night long,
It was March 12th.
It was very cold.
And then,
We see a long convoy of men passing by, coming from what was called the Russian camp.
because it had been built by the Russians,
which was in fact the turnaround,
the infirmary.
And they were ghosts.
First of all,
They were naked.
So they had blankets on them, like the Muslims.
like that,
or some kind of towel tied around it,
in front of the genitals.
Then they simply didn't care.
They didn't care about being naked.
They were passing by,
like that.
It was epic.
They gassed 3500 of them in those last eight days.
not to mention all the others we killed here and there,
But in this case, they were completely exterminated at the very end.
So, of course, that didn't make us happy.
And besides, it worried us about our own fate.
We were saying to each other,
There's no reason why we should be released when we're in the process of killing these people.
And those who were alive,
if you can call it living,
We were the living dead,
We were led on a walk and we arrived at a gate.
the guards on each side,
us in the middle.
And the people who were inside the camp,
in front of the gate,
they told us,
to announce some good news to us,
The Germans are not allowed to enter this camp.
And there is one among us,
when she was just the foot.
In that portal,
She turned around and spat in the supervisor's face.
I think we all would have wanted to do the same thing.
But we were so exhausted that we no longer had the strength to move.
And we were told that we were in Theresienstadt.
in Czechoslovakia,
and that we are protected in this camp by the Red Cross.
And then suddenly we hear cries of joy,
It was frantic,
And those were the first ones, the ones in front of us.
who arrived in...
at the place where all the trucks were parked.
And the truck drivers,
They were American soldiers prisoners in their uniforms.
And they were Black.
So there are no black SS officers.
It was insane.
She wanted to embrace the poor Black people who couldn't love in the face of these filthy ghosts,
filth,
stinky
who were retreating and saying to themselves,
They're going to eat us alive.
And so,
It was crazy.
Me too,
when I arrived,
I didn't want to kiss Black people.
because there were people in front of me.
SO,
They gave us American cigarettes.
The smell of cigarettes.
I don't smoke.
But that smell,
when I feel it,
I'm immersed again.
I am free once again in Mattausen.
And that's only on April 23rd.
on the banks of the Elbe,
But we had taken refuge in a house to be safe from the bombings,
that I was liberated by the Red Army.
And they were shouting at us,
That's it,
We are free.
The Russian is arriving.
Some of them were going crazy.
I saw someone throw themselves over there,
through this balcony,
who fell.
I think people didn't realize.
I think they were crazy to do something like that.
We said to each other in moments like these,
Suicide is pointless.
When we went outside,
we checked,
There was a baker's cart loaded with bread in front of the house.
And on this bread,
a soldier of the Red Army,
legs apart,
who launched the...
the pine trees of the cart to the population that surrounded it.
That's how we received our first Liberty Pine.
And it was only from that moment on that repatriation options became available to us.
And that's where I was already saying it,
I did not choose Germany.
I have chosen France again.
I told everyone,
I'm going to France.
They looked at me as if I were crazy.
A woman was telling me,
But you're going to France,
But do you...
How are you going to get to France?
Do you realize?
We are in Czechoslovakia,
France is far away.
I didn't want to hear anything.
I didn't want to know anything.
From where the house came back to me,
the parents,
The discussions?
who spoke of France as if it were the promised land,
French culture,
the French Revolution.
My father, who had hoped to conduct an orchestra in Paris,
He said it with a smile.
without really believing it,
But anyway.
The rivalry wasn't fun.
We felt like subhumans.
animals,
It was almost like being at camp.
We were made to arrive in a line.
We were sprinkled with...
DTs,
I believe,
That was it.
This white powder,
there,
Good,
We eventually understood that they were afraid of typhus.
but we still found it offensive.
We were completely white.
completely white hair
It smelled bad.
It was unpleasant.
It stung.
We were furious.
And then at the end of the fifth day,
I was told,
Good,
You go home.
And so I boarded a train where there were only prisoners of war.
So when they saw me,
They asked me what I was doing there.
and I told them I was a...
They called me a German girl.
What were you doing in Germany?
they told me.
For a little while,
They would have beaten me.
This is the first time since my arrest that I've been afraid.
I thought to myself,
I escaped from the camp.
Those guys are going to rip me to shreds.
And then in the transfer...
to get from the train station to my house,
We stopped at an aunt's house.
At an aunt's house, who had summoned me when my mother told her I was resisting, to tell me that if ever,
that I knew very well that the Germans had said that if they did not arrest the resistance fighters,
They could arrest families.
the brothers,
the fathers,
the cousins,
everyone.
And that they wouldn't let themselves be arrested without having done anything wrong.
that they would be forced to denounce me.
She told me that,
the aunt.
And when we went back,
We stopped by this aunt's house, who had always been a little unwell, to say hello.
But me,
I still remembered his warning.
And what do I find when I get out of the car to give him a kiss on his radio?
A beautiful photo of me all grown up like this with a lovely tricolour ribbon and a bow.
I burst out laughing.
I couldn't stop.
I stopped laughing because I found it so ridiculous.
Like this France, whether collaborating or passive,
and then suddenly, heroically,
with tricolour cockades on the photo of the heroes.
My uncle told me,
You know, they're all alive.
And me, that's it.
It killed me.
All alive.
So he wanted to talk about my parents, of course, and my family.
But I was thinking about all the others there.
I learned that my brother died a month before the liberation.
that he let himself die.
By saying that Frenia is no longer here,
I no longer have a reason to live.
When we returned,
The Jewish problem was completely ignored.
It was all about the resistance fighters.
Jews did not exist.
They came back just like any of us,
no difference.
And they were worse off...
mistreated,
because initially,
They were not given a pension.
Rather, they had the pension of what were called politicians.
that is to say, a pittance,
Therefore, they were misidentified.
Often,
They were foreigners.
So they were having difficulties.
Arrested in France,
They were returning to France.
People who had taken refuge from Poland or elsewhere,
They were in incredibly difficult circumstances.
And what's more, they were ashamed.
That's for sure.
Perhaps she was ashamed of not having fought.
Yet,
There were many Jews in the resistance.
There was resistance to Moses,
a significant Jewish resistance.
But the vast majority of people,
anyway,
They were quite passive.
In my opinion,
They couldn't do otherwise.
I can't picture a woman with four kids fighting off the police who came to arrest her.
In addition,
They were arrested by the French gendarmerie.
almost all by himself.
But this arbitrary separation also exists between resistance and genocide,
whereas it was part of a broader policy,
This is, in my opinion, a serious mistake.
I think that perhaps history will restore some form of unity to the massacre.
That's why I've always said...
And I told them again that none of us,
Normally,
He should not return because a dictatorship prioritizes the elimination of opponents of the dictatorship.
And sometimes,
somewhat incidentally,
scapegoats.
Good,
But that's already one thing.
SO,
I think things will still be okay...
Indeed, it's better when we don't say, for example, to someone who was deported, "So you're Jewish," as if only Jews were deported.
sometimes leads to this error as well
So, me,
for a long time,
I didn't mention deportation.
except when it was just the two of us.
because I felt that people were interested,
They didn't care.
like in the year 40,
There was no point in telling them the stuff.
And then in 1980,
THE...
The negotiators,
revisionists,
we said first,
And then later the deniers appeared in our institutions.
We thought to ourselves,
Something needs to be done.
We know that things have been done.
gas chambers, of which we know how many people were imprisoned.
what concentration camps were like.
We can at least make ourselves heard as much as they do.
So we need to make sure people listen to us.
Let us be heard.
When we started testifying, we thought we would warn young people.
We're going to tell them what happened.
That will make them think.
They will know how to vote.
We were deluding ourselves.
And gradually,
When you see things deteriorating like that,
and take this turn which is beyond our control.
this religious twist,
I would say.
We are powerless.
Our testimony is useless.
But it's true that I no longer really know how to glimpse any hope today.
When I think that we've embarked on preemptive wars,
to wage humanitarian wars.
Good,
It's true that we no longer understand why people choose war for...
I would say,
to improve or import democracy,
because, quite obviously,
In my opinion,
This is not the right solution to give humanity a future.
Who benefits from wars?
It's always the same thing.
We believe we are dying for our country.
Well, that's it.
I think it doesn't exist anymore.
People were already dying for heavy industry.
whether it be the De Vendel family,
the Krupp or
Thyssen, and today it's the same,
It's Enron.
Papa Bush,
Rumsfeld and the others who want Iraqi oil,
who lied to wage war.
People always lie to wage war.
Hitler lied to the Germans when he said there was a race superior to all other races, and the German people believed him.